Finding Aid for the Alfred Leland Crabb/William Rodney Cline Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Alfred Leland Crabb/William Rodney Cline Collection
1933-1979
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0090
.84 linear feet
Biographical Sketch
Alfred Leland Crabb
Alfred Leland Crabb was a well-known educator and novelist, born in Warren County, Kentucky on January 22, 1884. He received his undergraduate degree from George Peabody College for Teachers, an Master of Arts from Columbia University, and a PhD from Peabody. After teaching and serving as principal in Louisiana and Kentucky, in 1916 he joined the faculty of Western Kentucky State Normal School. In 1927, he became a professor at Peabody, where he remained until he retired in 1950.
In addition to his professional work, he was keenly interested in history, especially that of Tennessee and Kentucky in the Civil War and Reconstruction era. He was the author of several historical novels; Dinner at Belmont and Supper at the Maxwell House, and biographical novels, such as Home to the Hermitage (Andrew Jackson) and Home to Kentucky (Henry Clay).
He was married to Bertha Gardner and had one son, Alfred L. Crabb, Jr. Alfred Leland Crabb died in Bowling Green, Kentucky on October 1, 1979.
William Rodney Cline
William Rodney Cline was born in Lake Charles, Louisiana on November 11, 1903. He received his undergraduate degree from Louisiana Tech, a Master of Arts from Louisiana State University, and a PhD from George Peabody College for Teachers. While at Peabody, he studied with Alfred Leland Crabb, and the two men and their wives enjoyed a lasting friendship.
From 1941-1944, Cline served as Dean of McNeese Junior College in Lake Charles, Louisiana. In 1944, he became Dean of Northeast Junior College of Louisiana State University, and 1950 he joined the faculty of Louisiana State University, where he remained until he retired in 1952. During his career, he was the author of six books, numerous pamphlets and over 50 published articles, many concerning the history of public education in Louisiana.
He was married to Mildred Elliott and had one daughter, Kathleen.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists primarily of the correspondence from 1933-1979 between Alfred Leland Crabb and William Rodney Cline, his former doctoral student at George Peabody College for Teachers. Found within this collection are letters from Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb and a few miscellaneous letters from the Crabbs and Clines to others. Rodney Cline’s autobiography and his family history are a part of the collection as well as some Cline family photos and mementoes.
Cline’s friendship with his mentor Crabb was of great importance to him and his wife. He wrote, in 1933, “Long before leaving Peabody and Nashville, Mrs. Cline and I both realized the benefit and happiness we were storing up for the future. What we did not realize.. .was that the threads of attachment then forming were becoming so strong as to be well-nigh unbreakable, the elasticity of their fibre being such that when stretched by time, distance, and other interests, their pull was increased thereby rather than diminished”. This collection is a testimony to those “threads of attachment”.
- Correspondence---Alfred Leland Crabb to Rodney Cline, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence---Alfred Leland Crabb to Rodney Cline, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence---Alfred Leland Crabb to Rodney Cline, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence---Alfred Leland Crabb to Rodney Cline, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Cline, 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, January-June, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline to Alfred Leland Crabb, July1978-May, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence---Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb, September 1933-March, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence---Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb, April 1968-December, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence---Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb, January 1970-November, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence---Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb, January 1972-December, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence---Mildred Cline to Bertha Crabb, January 1974-May, 1977 and 4 undated letters (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence---Miscellaneous Correspondence of Alfred Leland Crabb and Rodney Cline to Others, 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence---Evelyn McCulloh to Alfred Leland Crabb, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence---Manuscripts. Of Songs by Rodney Cline, 1948, 1949, and Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline, Writings---Personal and Professional (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline---Autobiography and Family History (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence---Rodney Cline---Personal Mementoes and Photographs (Box 2, Folder 13)